Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, Montgomery County Branch Papers, 1754-1996
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, Montgomery County Branch Papers, 1754-1996
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1962-001
13 boxes; 6.0 cu. ft.
The records largely document the recent history of Smithfield Plantation, ancestral home of the Preston family, focusing particularly on its restoration beginning in 1962. While much of the renovation occurred in the 1960s, many of the records detail other renovation projects done in the 1970s and 1980s. The collection also includes historical and other related documents dating from before the original Preston family's residence at Smithfield.
Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, Montgomery County Branch
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, Montgomery County Branch Papers were donated to Special Collections between 1962 and 1996.
Biographical/Historical Information
Founded in 1889, the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities (APVA) has twenty branches which own and maintain historic properties. In November 1958 the APVA authorized the organization of the Montgomery County branch for the specific purpose of acquiring and restoring Smithfield Plantation, the historic home near Blacksburg in Montgomery County, Virginia, built by William Preston in 1773. In 1959 Mrs. Janie Preston Brockenbrough Lamb, a descendant of Preston, donated Smithfield and 4.5 acres of land to the APVA. Restoration of the building was begun in 1962 when the APVA's Montgomery County Branch raised the funds for renovation and contracted with architects and contractors.
Smithfield Plantation is the historic home of the Preston family, one of the founding families of Blacksburg and Montgomery County, Virginia. It was built by William Preston (1729-83), who emigrated from northern Ireland with his family in 1737. He married Susanna Smith in 1761 and settled at Greenfield in Botetourt County in 1769. Preston established himself as a leader in the Virginia frontier by serving in the militia in the French and Indian and Revolutionary wars, in the House of Burgesses representing Augusta County from 1766 to 1768 and Botetourt County in 1769, and as County Lieutenant of Fincastle and Montgomery. He was appointed surveyor of Fincastle County in 1772 and moved his family to that area. He built Smithfield, named in honor of his wife, in 1773. Smithfield was the birthplace and home of three Virginia governors, including James Patton Preston (son of William), and John Buchanan Floyd and John Floyd, Jr. (grandsons of William).
George Green Shackelford, a professor of history from 1954 to 1986 (now Emeritus) at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, or Virginia Tech, which is adjacent to the Smithfield property, spearheaded the restoration by forming the Montgomery County branch and adopting the project of preserving and restoring the Smithfield residence.
Scope and Content
The records largely document the recent history of Smithfield Plantation, ancestral home of the Preston family, focusing particularly on its restoration beginning in 1962. While much of the renovation occurred in the 1960s, many of the records detail other renovation projects done in the 1970s and 1980s. The collection is organized into seven series: Series I: Correspondence(largely from and to George Shackelford); Series II: Publications, including APVA and Montgomery County branch newsletters and APVA Discovery magazines; Series III: Smithfield Plantation Renovation, including appraisals, reports, and receipts; SeriesIV: Renovations of other Smithfield Plantation Buildings, including information about the renovations of other structures on the Smithfield property, (the cook's cabin, the miller's log house, and the smokehouse); Series V: AVPA General Files, including meeting minutes, financial reports, and building committee reports; Series VI: Historical Documents from dating from the original Preston family's residence at Smithfield (materials include manuscript account books (1754-63) of William Preston while residing at Greenfield, manuscript pages detailing work done by a wheelright (1845-50); and genealogical information about the Preston family); and Series VII: Miscellaneous Documents, which includes materials relating to historic Montgomery County and the Smithfield Plantation. The collection also contains an oversize folder with blueprints and architectural drawings.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by series. Wherever possible, materials are arranged chronologically within each series.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections houses a number of other collections containing information on the Preston family and Smithfield Plantation:
John Preston Deed, 1826. Ms2005-014.
John Preston Papers, 1806-1830, 1844, n.d. Ms94-034
Preston Family (Alice Preston Moore Collection) Papers, 1745-1882. Ms1962-004.
Preston Family (Charles Peale Didier Collection) Papers, 1747-1897. Ms85-020.
Robert Taylor Preston Papers, 1829-1871, n.d. Ms92-003.
William Preston Land Grant, 1773. Ms94-027.
George Green Shackelford Papers, ca.1955-1986. Ms83-003. This collection is unprocessed and has some access restrictions. Please contact Special Collections for further information.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Preston family, Montgomery County, Va.
Corporate Names:
Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities (APVA)
Subjects:
Blacksburg (Va.); Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.); Smithfield Plantation House (Blacksburg, Va.)
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1958-1988
  - Correspondence to APVA members, 1961-1970 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Correspondence about the Civil War Centennial, 1958-1964 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Correspondence and photographs to and from Howe P. Cochran, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence to/from Charles W. Crush, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence to/from and newspaper articles about the Daughters of the American Revolution (DAR), 1962-64, and DAR May 1961 and August-September 1963 magazines. (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspondence to/from Preston Davie, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Correspondence to/from Virginia Drewry, 1960-1965 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Correspondence to/from Virginia Farrier, Marion Fuller, Mary Fray, and Preston Fox III, 1960-1963 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Correspondence to/from and newspaper articles about the Garden Club of Virginia, 1969-1894 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Correspondence to/from Preston P. Joyes, 1960-1965 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Correspondence to/from Mrs. Lamb (includes newspaper articles about her death), 1958-1965 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Correspondence to/from Brockenbrough Lamb Jr. (includes newspaper articles about his death), 1960-1964 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Correspondence on Cyrus Hall McCormick Historical Site, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Correspondence to/from William Tayloe Munford (Smithfield Plantation interior decorator), 1963-1965 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Correspondence about the National Trust for Historic Preservation, 1959-1963 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Correspondence to/from Sarah Caperton Preston and Nelly C. Preston, 1961-1964 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Correspondence to/from Marguerite Stuart Quarles, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Correspondence about the National Trust Summer School (summer study abroad programs), 1958-1964 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Correspondence to/from Mrs. W. Taliaferro Thompson, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence to/from George Shackelford, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence to/from George Shackelford, 1960 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence to/from George Shackelford, 1961 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence to/from George Shackelford (includes photographs of paintings, misc.), 1962 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence to/from George Shackelford, 1963 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence to/from George Shackelford, 1964 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence to/from George Shackelford, 1965 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence to/from George Shackelford, 1967-1970 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence to/from George Shackelford, 1975-1979 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence to/from George Shackelford (includes obituaries of William P. Mounfield), 1980-1988 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence to/from George Shackelford, n.d (Box-folder 3:4)
- Series II: Publications, 1959-1989
  - Newspaper articles about Smithfield Plantation, 1959-1969 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Copies of newspaper articles about Smithfield Plantation, 1960-1963 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Newspaper articles about Smithfield Plantation, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Newspaper articles about Smithfield Plantation, 1980-1984 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - APVA Discovery magazines, [Fall 1977; Spring and Fall 1978; Spring and Fall 1980; Summer 1981; Fall/Winter 1982; Winter 1982; Winter 1983; 1984-85 annual reports; 1986-88; and Centennial 1989], 1977-1989 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - APVA newsletters (Vol. I, no. 1 through Vol. VI, no. 3), 1983-1988 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Montgomery County Branch APVA newsletters, [Jan. 1981; Feb. 1983; Jan. 1984; May 1985; Jan. 1986; Mar. and Oct. 1987; Mar., Jun., and Nov. 1988; and Jun. 1989], 1981-1989 (Box-folder 3:11)
- Series III: Smithfield Plantation Renovation, 1899-1989
  - Photographs and negatives of Smithfield Plantation, 1899-1967 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Smithfield Plantation titles, copies of deeds, appraisals, and plats, 1904-1963 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Acquisition of Smithfield Plantation property (initial proposal, APVA acceptance, Montgomery County Branch APVA Constitution & By-Laws), 1958-1962 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Correspondence to/from G.E. Trout & Sons, General Contractors at Smithfield Plantation, 1959-1963 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Smithfield Plantation historical information, restoration plan, and budget plan for operations, 1960 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Roof shingles for Smithfield Plantation, 1960 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Financing for the restoration of Smithfield Plantation, 1960-1963 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Process of renovation at Smithfield Plantation (architect and contractor correspondence), 1960-1964 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Photocopies of layouts and blueprints for Smithfield Plantation, 1960-1982 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Correspondence about refurnishing Smithfield Plantation, 1961-1981 (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Notepaper and postal cards for Smithfield Plantation, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Correspondence from Guerrant & Mounfield, architects for Smithfield Plantation restoration, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Smithfield Plantation restoration correspondence, sketches, and photographs, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Smithfield Plantation restoration bills and correspondence, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Information about furniture (appraisals, gifts, purchases, shipping orders, and photographs), 1962-1965 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - "Specifications for Restoration of Smithfield Plantation House," copy 1, by Guerrant & Mounfield, A.I.A. Architects, 1963 (Box-folder 5:6)
  - "Specifications for Restoration of Smithfield Plantation House," duplicate of copy 1, by Guerrant & Mounfield, A.I.A. Architects, 1963 (Box-folder 5:7)
  - "Proposed Landscape Plan for Smithfield Plantation" by Philip John Markham, 1967 (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Montgomery County Branch APVA archeological project at Smithfield Plantation, 1967-1975 (Box-folder 5:9)
  - "A Report on an Excavation at Smithfield Plantation House" (trench excavation along the south side of the main house and office excavation) by K.R. Bonnett and J.D. Lahendro, and Quarterly Bulletin of Archeological Society of Virginia, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 5:10)
  - Smithfield Plantation proposal for public restroom sites, 1977 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Smithfield Plantation Accessions Committee Report. Accession are of furniture, "Janie Preston" doll, rugs from Howe Preston Cockran, and Indian artifacts, donated to Smithfield, 1980 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - "Archeological Testing of 44MY97, Smithfield Plantation" (location of cultural deposits on grounds north of main house) by Herbert G. Fisher, 1982 (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Smithfield Plantation capital funds drive, 1982 (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Smithfield Plantation improvements for water and sewer, 1982 (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Smithfield Plantation reconstruction notes and fees, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Smithfield Plantation restroom project, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 6:7)
  - "Archeological Testing of Walkway Feature 44MY97, Smithfield Plantation" by Herbert G. Fisher (includes slides and photographs), 1983 (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Smithfield Plantation building committee report, 1984 (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Smithfield Plantation building committee, 1984 (Box-folder 6:10)
  - Smithfield Plantation contracts with Don Loop, Inc., Masonry and building contractor, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Smithfield Plantation air conditioning correspondence (includes photographs), 1984-1989 (Box-folder 6:12)
  - Smithfield Plantation storm window specs and catalogs; possible donations for windows, 1985 (Box-folder 6:13)
  - Smithfield Plantation organization and operations, 1985 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Smithfield Plantation building committee (includes photographs), 1985-1986 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Smithfield Plantation budgets and plans, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 7:3)
  - "Air Conditioning Study for Smithfield Plantation Main House" by Mills, Oliver, & Webb, Inc., Architects, 1986 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Smithfield Plantation curator contract, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Smithfield Plantation building committee, 1986-1990 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Smithfield Plantation pest control records, 1986-1990 (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Smithfield Plantation well abandonment, Roanoke Pump Sales & Service, 1987 (Box-folder 7:8)
  - "Central Chimney Base Excavation, Smithfield Plantation" by Woods River Construction Co. (includes photographs), 1987 (Box-folder 7:9)
  - Smithfield Plantation beam reinforcement (includes photographs), 1987 (Box-folder 8:1)
  - Information on cedar shingles and shakes for Smithfield Plantation, 1987 (Box-folder 8:2)
  - "New Air Conditioning System, Smithfield Plantation" by Mills, Oliver, & Webb, Inc., Architects, 1987 (Box-folder 8:3)
  - Smithfield Plantation waterproofing (includes photographs and negatives), 1987-1988 (Box-folder 8:4)
  - Smithfield Plantation air conditioning, Mills, Oliver, & Webb Inc., Architects, 1987-19883 (Box-folder 8:5)
  - Smithfield Plantation air conditioning, Woods River Company, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 8:6)
  - Smithfield Plantation air conditioning controls and schematics, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 8:7)
  - Smithfield Plantation building committee, bills paid, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 8:8)
  - Smithfield Plantation air conditioning, Air Control Corporation, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 9:1)
  - Smithfield Plantation painting specifications and catalogs, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 9:2)
  - Smithfield Plantation interior painting, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 9:3)
  - "Smithfield Plantation, Historic Paint Research Report: The Interior Woodwork" by Matthew John Mosca, 1989 (Box-folder 9:4)
  - Smithfield Plantation letterhead and envelopes. (Box-folder 9:5)
  - "Specifications for the Restoration of Smithfield Plantation House" by Mounfield and Nichols, A.I.A. Architects. (Box-folder 9:6)
  - Smithfield Plantation Restoration booklet. (Box-folder 9:7)
  - Smithfield Plantation blueprint and sketches for the relocation of heat pumps. (Box-folder 9:8)
- Series IV: Renovations of other Smithfield Plantation Buildings, 1970-1986
  - Smithfield Plantation Cook's Cabin restoration, 1970 (Box-folder 9:9)
  - "Restoration of Miller's Log House, Establishment of Water Source for Mill, and Eventual Reconstruction of Grist Mill" by William L. Favrao, 1976 (Box-folder 9:10)
  - "Outline Specifications for Restoration and Remodeling of the Miller's House and Site Water and Sewer Lines" by Rogers & Reynolds Architects, Inc., 1982 (Box-folder 9:11)
  - Application for funds for Cook's Cabin, Miller's House, and water and sewer, 1982 (Box-folder 9:12)
  - "Outline Specifications for 1) Restoration and Remodeling of the Miller's House and 2) Site Water and Sewer Lines, Smithfield Plantation" by Rogers & Reynolds Architects, Inc. (includes photographs), 1982 (Box-folder 9:13)
  - Smithfield Plantation Smokehouse contract, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 9:14)
  - Smithfield Plantation Cook's Cabin and Smokehouse restoration, 1986 (Box-folder 10:1)
  - Contract Documents, Cook's Cabin Enclosure, Smithfield Plantation, 1986 (Box-folder 10:2)
  - Smithfield Plantation enclosure of Cook's Cabin and restoration of Weaver's Cabin, 1986-1990 (Box-folder 10:3)
  - Photographs of the Miller's Log House. (Box-folder 10:4)
- Series V: AVPA General Files, 1899-1989
  - APVA Souvenir of the Midsummer Night's Dream (souvenir book containing history and board members of APVA, play committees, and advertisements), 1899 (Box-folder 10:5)
  - Montgomery County Branch APVA membership and financial records, 1957-1970 (Box-folder 10:6)
  - Montgomery County Branch APVA Constitution & By-laws, annual reports, meeting agendas/notes, membership list, 1957-1971 (Box-folder 10:7)
  - Montgomery County Branch APVA minutes and records (bound book), 1959-1963 (Box-folder 10:8)
  - APVA mailing lists, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 11:1)
  - Montgomery County Branch APVA minutes, 1963-1979 (Box-folder 11:2)
  - Newspaper clippings about Smithfield Plantation, 1973-1988 (Box-folder 11:3)
  - Purchase of 7.11 acres of Smithfield Plantation property from estate of Janie B. Lamb, 1979 (Box-folder 11:4)
  - Montgomery County Branch APVA minutes, 1979-1894 (Box-folder 11:5)
  - APVA accessions policy and accessions of items for Smithfield Plantation, 1980-1989 (Box-folder 11:6)
  - Montgomery County Branch APVA minutes, financial reports, and building committee reports, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 11:7)
  - Montgomery County Branch APVA handbook (minutes, budgets and budget reports, members, by-laws, maps, and copies of photographs), 1984-1990 (Box-folder 11:8)
  - Montgomery County Branch APVA amended by-laws, 1985 (Box-folder 12:1)
  - Montgomery County Branch APVA minutes, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 12:2)
  - APVA Branch Operating Manual prepared for the Montgomery County Branch, 1987 (Box-folder 12:3)
  - Information about the APVA Centennial Celebration, 1989 (Box-folder 12:4)
- Series VI: Historical Documents, 1754-1826
  - Manuscript account book of William Preston of Greenfield, 1754-1759 (Box-folder 12:5)
  - Manuscript account book of William Preston of Greenfield, 1755-1763 (Box-folder 12:6)
  - Original document of tax document on William Preston's estate, 1805 (Box-folder 12:7)
  - Manuscript pages detailing work done by a wheelright, 1845-1850 (Box-folder 12:8)
  - James Cochran's handwritten copy of Mrs. Letitia Floyd's 1843 manuscript of History of the Preston Family, done by Cochran in 1848. Includes a typescript transcription by June Stubbs, 1996 (Box-folder 12:9)
  - Obituary notice of Mrs. Louisa Penelope Preston, 1853 (Box-folder 12:10)
  - E.L. Hawkins manuscript book of his Blacksburg business general ledger accounts, 1895 (Box-folder 12:11)
  - Envelope with piece of flax spun by Margaret Buchanan Campbell (the envelope has a written account of the history of the flax--"Charles Campbell was placed in jail because he was unable to pay all his taxes. His wife, Margaret, spun flax thread to sell. She was able to get her husband out of jail and pay their taxes with the money she made from the thread"), 1907 (Box-folder 12:12)
  - Letter to Mrs. J.S. Grasty from Monica McPherson, 1932 (Box-folder 12:13)
  - Poem by Kathleen Shelor Bibb, "Smithfield" Ancestor of V.P.I., 1964 (Box-folder 12:14)
  - Typed copy of The Will of Colonel William Preston, The Radford Review, Faculty Research Issue, 1972 (Box-folder 12:15)
  - Inventory of Preston papers and correspondence about appraisals, 1985 (Box-folder 12:16)
  - "Archeological Investigation of the Governor John Floyd and Letitia Preston Floyd Graves, Sweet Springs, Monroe County, West Virginia" by Kenneth W. Robinson, 1988 (Box-folder 12:17)
  - Geneology of the Preston family. (Box-folder 12:18)
  - Copy of text written on John Preston's monument at Tinkling Spring Cemetery. (Box-folder 12:19)
  - Photograph copy of the Preston Family and the Civil War. (Box-folder 12:20)
  - Typescript list of the account of property William Preston owned when he died on June 28, 1793 (Box-folder 12:21)
  - Photocopy of list of the personal estate of James P. Preston. (Box-folder 12:22)
  - Photocopies of Susanna Smith Preston's last will and testament (1822), inventory of goods (1825), and account of property sold (1826). (Box-folder 12:23)
  - Colonel William Preston and His Illustrious Progeny, by George Shackelford. (Box-folder 12:24)
  - Smithfield Plantation. (Box-folder 12:25)
  - Poem by Hyde Fowlkes, Smithfield. (Box-folder 12:26)
  - Photograph of Thomas Lewis Preston. (Box-folder 12:27)
  - Copies of drawings of William Lynn Lewis, Mary Preston Lewis, Margaret Lynn Lewis Cochran, John Cochran, with a brief history on the back of each. (Box-folder 12:28)
- Series VII: Miscellaneous Documents, 1959-1986
  - National Trust for Historic Preservation printed material, 1959-1964 (Box-folder 13:1)
  - Information about the tourist industry from the U.S. Department of Commerce and correspondence about creating a commission to study the tourist industry, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 13:2)
  - Acceptance and thank you notes to the Preservation of Restored Grounds and Garden of Smithfield Plantation, hosted by the Garden Club of Virginia, 1984 (Box-folder 13:3)
  - Resume and letter of recommendation for Jeffrey Clayton Turner, Smithfield Plantation resident curator, 1985 (Box-folder 13:4)
  - Notes on Virginia publications, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 13:5)
  - "Williams Mill Report" (Valley Roller Mill restoration, includes photographs and negatives), 1986 (Box-folder 13:6)
  - Typed geneology on the Montgomery and Graham family. (Box-folder 13:7)
  - Copy of historical map of Montgomery County. (Box-folder 13:8)
  - Photographs and negatives of Cane Mill at Mabry Mill. (Box-folder 13:9)
  - iscellaneous unidentified pen sketches of lake scenes and trees (artist unknown). (Box-folder 13:10)
  - Copy of "Park Planning Guidelines" by George E. Fogg. (Box-folder 13:11)
  - Brochures and pamphlets about Jamestown (historic property owned by APVA). (Box-folder 13:12)
  - Old Church Tower at Jamestown by Chas. W. Smith. (Box-folder 13:13)
- Oversize Folders, 1962-1990
  - Smithfield Plantation restoration blueprints, 1962-1963 (Folder 1)
  - Smithfield Plantation restoration drawings, 1962-1965 (Folder 2)
  - Smithfield Plantation restoration drawings, 1963-1965 (Folder 3)
  - Smithfield Plantation restoration blueprints, 1963-1965 (Folder 4)
  - Smithfield Plantation Miller's Cabin restoration drawings, 1980-1982 (Folder 5)
  - Smithfield Plantation restoration blueprints, 1982-1990 (Folder 6)
  - Smithfield Plantation Log Cabin restoration blueprints, 1990 (Folder 7)
  - Topo of Smithfield Plantation, 1974 (Item 1)